Rebecca Bailey

♦ Chicago, IL / Seattle, WA
♦ becca.is
♦ beccanelsonbailey@gmail.com
in beccanelsonmakesthings
♦ beccaliz

Node.js

Technical Skills

React ***

HTML+CSS ★★★

Ruby & Rails *

Angular (2+)

GraphQL + Apollo ★★★

About Me

Code I care about using the best tools available to solve technical problems. I am especially interested in the user-facing parts of our applications, and continually learning how to use front-end development and design to create the best possible experience for the user.

Team building I have led successful planning meetings and retros, participated in hiring decisions, and I am always learning to give effective feedback and build stronger development teams.

Mentoring As a former teacher, my favorite part of my job is mentoring and sharing my knowledge. I mentored an apprentice throughout most of 2018, and was a PDM (Professional Development Manager) for three junior-level developers.

Diversity and I was the chair of 8th Light's Diversity, Culture and Inclusion committee, and each of my jobs I have been focused on improving recruitment, retention, and advancement for underrepresented minorities in technology.

Experience

Software Engineer - The Mom Project - Chicago, IL - May-August 2019

The Mom Project is a startup that helps women find flexible work opportunities. I worked on a small team that was starting to take ownership of a Rails and React legacy codebase. I worked on new features and bugfixes, and developed a JavaScript style guide to help the team standardize our React code.

8th Light - Chicago, IL - April 2016—March 2019

Lead Software Crafter - June 2018—March 2019 Software Crafter - November 2016—June 2018 Resident Apprentice - April 2016—November 2016

I worked as a software consultant, working with many different teams to develop new products or work on existing legacy codebases. Most of my work was focused on front-end development using Angular and React, with occasional work in various other full-stack frameworks. As a consultant, I was responsible for building relationships with clients and participating in product development. See section above for more information about my mentoring and diversity and inclusion work.

Data and Research Panelist - Ingenuity - Chicago, IL - September 2016—June 2018

Ingenuity is a non-profit organization that supports fine arts programs in the Chicago Public Schools. Each year, Ingenuity collects data on fine arts programs across the city, and uses that data to create an online guide called the artlook map. I served on an advisory panel that focused on Ingenuity's collection and use of data to improve fine arts education.

Music and Fine Arts Teacher - Various - January 2011—June 2015

Given the opportunity, I would love to tell you more about my experiences teaching both in the United States and overseas. I have taught both as a full-time teacher in one school and a traveling teaching artist at multiple schools.

Rebecca Bailey

😚 Chicago, IL / Seattle, WA **6** becca.is beccanelsonbailey@gmail.com **in** beccanelsonmakesthings **y** beccaliz

Education and Training

Dev Bootcamp Completed 19-week web development program focused on full-stack Chicago, IL development, including Ruby on Rails, JavaScript, web servers, database September 2015 - January 2016 management, and courses in Engineering Empathy.

August 2006 - May 2010

Anderson University Bachelor of Music in Music Education

Anderson, IN Anderson University Honors Program

Speaking

React Conf The State of React State in 2019

Lake Las Vegas, NV October 2019

FullStack London Beyond the WAT: Why Component Design Still Matters

July 2019

London, UK Workshop - Design Patterns for State Management in React and Typescript

RVA Javascript JavaScript Survival Skills

Richmond, VA November 2018

Chicago JS Camp JavaScript Survival Skills

Chicago, IL September 2018

Technical Writing

Personal Blog Design Pattens for State Management in React and Typescript

July 15, 2019

8th Light Blog A New Approach to State Management with the React Context API

November 20, 2018

8th Light Blog Dependency Inversion in React with Render Props

August 30, 2018

8th Light Blog Two Design Patterns You're Probably Already Using

May 22, 2017